<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>I Iohn Penry, doo heare as I shall answere before the Lord my God in that great day of iudgement set downe sumarily the whole truth and nothing but the truth which I hold and professe at this hower eyther in regard of my faith towards my God and dread soueraigne Queene Elizabeth unto whome only of all the potentas in the world I owe all reuerente, dutie and submission in the Lord.</title>
            <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100448</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836288</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836288</idno>
            <idno type="VID">548</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09295)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1356:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>I Iohn Penry, doo heare as I shall answere before the Lord my God in that great day of iudgement set downe sumarily the whole truth and nothing but the truth which I hold and professe at this hower eyther in regard of my faith towards my God and dread soueraigne Queene Elizabeth unto whome only of all the potentas in the world I owe all reuerente, dutie and submission in the Lord.</title>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed abroad :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1593?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Probably issued with "To my beloved wife Helener Penry" (STC 19610).--STC.</note>
                  <note>Several pages cropped, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Allegiance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Royal supremacy (Church of England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wales --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="testimonial">
            <pb facs="tcp:548:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:548:1"/>
            <p>I IOHN PENRY DOO HEARE AS I SHALL ANSWERE BEFORE THE LORD MY GOD IN that great day of Iudgement ſet downe ſumarily the Whole truth and nothing but the truth which I hold and profeſſe at this hower eyther in regard of my faith towards my God and Dread Soueraigne Queene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth unto whome only of all the potentas In the world I owe all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerente, dutie and ſubmiſſion in the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt / becauſe my allegeance vnto her Majeſties: is cheifly called In queſtion / that I am not at this day / nor yet euer was in all my life ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther guilty or priuie in any purpoſe / conſultation or intent of any ſedition againſt or diſturbance of her Majeſties Royall ſtate a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d peaceable govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And if I were priuie vnto any ſuch godleſe wicked and vndutifull actions or purpoſes as might any ways impayre or diſquiet the peaceae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſtate of my native prince and countrie I would reveale diſcloſe / and withſtand the ſame to the vtmoſt of my power in all perſons both foraigne and domeſticall of what proſſeſſion or religion ſoever they be.</p>
            <p>Her ſupreance authorite within her realmes and dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s I acknowledge to be ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all perſons in all cauſes / as no perſon eyther ciuill or eccleſiaſtical / may exempt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe or his cauſe from the power and cenſure of her lawes and ſword. I doe alſo ackno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wledge that her Majeſtie hath full authorite from the Lord by hir Royall power to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhe and enact all lawes both eccleſiaſticall and ciuill among hir ſubiectes: In the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king whereof the Lord requireth that hir ecleſiaſticall be warented by his writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word / wich expreſſely conteyneth whatſoever belongeth to his worſhip: &amp; her ciuill to be gron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the rules of common iuſtice and equitie / the wich boundes are ſo farr from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing from the authoritie of kings and princes / as they are the onely inexpugnable waies therof. This ſoueraigne prerogatiue authority of her hignes I am moſt willingly reddy to deffend and maintaine / againſt all the eſtates / perſons / and creatures vnder heaven to the loſſe of my life te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne touſandes tymes if it ſhould be neefull. And I take the lorde to record that / that day to my knowlege hath not paſſed over my head I a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſure ſince the firſt that the lord vnder her gratious raigne broght me to the knowledge of the truth / wherein I have not or doe not pray for the bleſſings of my God both outoward &amp; inward to be powred with afull horne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir right excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Maieſties Throne Regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; domini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons for ever &amp; ever: And that he would eyther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert / or ſpedily overthrowe In his wrath all his and hir ennaemies with their entrepriſes whether they be home or foraigne Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I cal the ſearcher of hartes as In wittnes of truth againſt my owne ſoule if eyther I di<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble / or forge in the premiſes. Secondly touching my faith / I doe beleve with my hart and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with my tongue that ther is no God but the true God only which that written word reacheth to be one in ſubſtance and three in perſon / the father / the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / and the holy goſt three diſtinct perſons of one and the ſelfe ſame ſubſtance. This moſt high God who alſo is my God in Chriſt Ieſus I veleeve to be the creator / preſeruer maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſoueraigne Lord and ſupreame commander of all creatures In heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and in earth men and Angels both good and bad. I doe beleeve that nothing doth or can comme to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> / but by the fore anointed and determinate wil / purpoſe / 
<pb facs="tcp:548:2"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> onely by gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the ſufferings and reghteouſnes of Chriſt Ieſus apprehended by true faith.</p>
            <p>Chriſt Ieſus In regard of his natures I beleve to be God &amp; man / even God alone bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for ever more: And in reſpect of his offices to be the onely king / Prieſt And Prophet of his Church / the which offices he ſo fully acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſſhed In the dayes of us fleſh by the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſting of the wholle will of his father thorough his preaching &amp; teaching the full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of his Chu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch / by his death and reſurr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction: and rec<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aving full abſolute power in heaven and in earth from his father / in ſuch ſorte as he is not to reteine a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor in any of theſe his offices / but is conſecrated alone to them all for euer more.</p>
            <p>True faith / I beleeve to be the perſuaſion of the harte where by the ſoule is truly aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of remiſſion of ſinnes and Imputation of righteo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſnes thorough Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This true faith belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth onely to Gods elect / and hath perſeuerance vnto the end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with this true faith alſo / is vnſeparably ioined (as the frut thereof) a dying vnto ſinne: and a living vnto righteouſnes in ſuch ſorte as the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſt have a continuall battel in them againſt ſinne. the wich by the power of Chriſts death is ſo wounded and in ſome meaſure decayeth more and more in them / vntil at l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngth it ſhall be vtterly conſumed whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bodies and ſoules be ſeparated / and not b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore.</p>
            <p>By the quickninge power of Chriſt / (I do beeleeue) that his here vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth are drawne more and more to like his bleſſed will and to practiſe the ſame / yea to give their liues ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to diſhonor their God in the will and voluntary deniall of his truth / and the breach of his lawes and wil / in any point revealed vnto them.</p>
            <p>His revealed will I beleeve to be perfet<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y conteined in the written word of the ould and newe teſtament given by the holy ghoſt for Inſtruction and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of his pore church as longe as the ſame is a pilgrime here vpon the earth.</p>
            <p>This Church I beleeve to be a companie of thoſe whom the word calleth ſaints which do not onely profeſſe in word that they knowe God / but alſo are ſubiect vnto his lawes and ordinance in deede: with this Church I do beleev<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the Lord God of is meere fauour hath entred into couenant that he will be their God / &amp; they ſhalbe his people the ſeales of this his convenant are only two / Baptiſme and the Lord ſupper.</p>
            <p>The Church here vpon earth / I do beleeve not to be perfect / although in regard of the order wich the Lord hath appointed for the ſame it be moſt abſolute / but to have manie blemiſhes and wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in it / yet I aſſuredly beleeve that all th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> true me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders thereof ſhall at the day of judgement receive their perfect conſumation by Ieſus Chriſt and be crowned in him with eternall glory of his meere grace / end not for anie merit of theirs.</p>
            <p>Thorough the mercies of my God / and therefore I am wilingly content to vndergoe my trouble in this life for his name ſake / who be glorified of my ſoule and body and of his ſaintes for ever more. Amen.</p>
            <p>I deteſt all hereſies / ſectes ſchimes / and errours wether newe or ould by whom ſoeuer they have be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted as puritiniſme / donatiſm<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Anabatiſterie Libertiniſme Brouniſme &amp; all the dreames and dotages of the familie of one but eſpecially all popery that moſt dred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full religion of Antichriſt: the great ennemie of the Lord Ieſus &amp; the moſt peſtilent aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarie of all the thrones of kings and princes. So that I abhorre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſoule that whole body a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d euery part of that Romiſh religion called the ſonne of perdition by the Spirit of God / becauſe the Lord hath determined vterly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume it by his appearinge in the bri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghtnes of his goſpell before his ſecond cominge.</p>
            <p>I deteſt that proud ſuperiority of this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinne whereby as the Apoſtle ſpake he hath exalted him ſelfe in his members and power to beare rule over the truth and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſteve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> over all that is caled holy: wholy oppoſeth himſelfe as moſt blodie aduerſary a gainſt all truths and ſeruants of the Lord which wil not ſuffer him with his ſard infer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall power toreigne over them inſtead of Chriſt in his bleſſed ordinances.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:548:2"/>
I deteſt in regard of theyr offices (I ſpeake not of the meanes perſones touching the Lords election) the head of that body the Pope his curſed triple crowne / his vſurped Iuridiction of eyther of both ſwords.</p>
            <p>I det<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt the limbes of that body / their ſpirituall powre / as Cardinals / Archbiſhop a Lord biſhops / Sufraganes / Abbots / Fryors / Deanes / Archdeacons / Commiſſaries / Chancelers / Officials / Munkfryers / Cannons / prebend Prieſts.</p>
            <p>I deteſt theyr invented maners of calling / wherby they are placed in their curſed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices / theyr deviſed workes wherin they are jmployed by reaſon of theyr offices / as the falſe doctrines and falſe worſhip of that kingdome with the livings and maintenances wherby they are maintayned in their offices. And foraſmuch as the members of Chriſt cannot have anie communion or fellowſhipe with anie of thoſe curſed jnuentions in ſo much as they can have no lawfull vſe or ſpirituall communion of / or with anie of theſe offices / callings / workes and maintenances / in ſo much as they cannot lawfullie be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto anie parte of the eccleſiaſticall power of theſe offices: Therfore it is that I dare not participat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in theſe aſſemblies over which anie of theſe officers b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are rule / or eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticallie jntermedle with the holy things of God / and where anie of theſe deviſed cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and non els / workes and maintenances are to be found: for I am forbidden to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve anie communion with theſe vnfructfull workes of darknes though it be vpon pr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of mining the truth and ſacraments of Chriſt / vpon payne of everlaſting formente day and night for evermore.</p>
            <p>Ad if I may not be ſubiect to the ceremonies of Moſes / as Circonciſion wich were ſometymes the Lords owne ſacred ordinances: how dare I or any other creature be in bondage vnto thoſe inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions of Antichriſt the greate enemy of the Lord Ieſus / whereof neyther the ſaincts of God can / neyther yet could have any ſanctified vſe.</p>
            <p>The truth of doctrine touching the trinitie and touching the natures and offices of Chriſt / Iuſtifying faith / Sacraments / externaly eſtabliſhed by her Maieſtie / profeſſed by her ſelfe / there H. H. &amp; ſuch as have knowledge in the aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies of this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: I acknowledge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my hart to be ſuch as if I mainteined not the vnitie &amp; held not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame doctrine with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thoſe points I could not poſſibly be ſaved / for out of that communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the true profeſſion which her Mieſtye hath eſtabliſhed in theſe and the like rules / the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is no hop of ſaluation: but to joine not with ſtanding with the publicke worſhip of theſe aſſemblies of the land / I dare not for the ſame reaſons.</p>
            <p>I more over willingly confeſſe that both of the teachers &amp; alſo of the profeſſors within theſe aſſemblyes of the land / have ſo imbraced this truth doctrine eſtabliſhed and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this land / that the Lord in his infinite goodnes hath graunted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fauor to ſhew out / wherein regard of Gods election I proteſt before men and Angels that I iudge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> members of the body whereof the ſonne of God Ieſus Chriſt is the head / onely herein the Lord be merciful vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as vnto my ſelfe in regard of my ſinnes / that they are not orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in that outward order which Chriſt Ieſus left in his Church but inſtead thereof are firſt ſubiect vnto thoſe forenamed offices / ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly / have co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ther falſe maner of callings vnto their offices: Thirdlie participate with a great parte of theyr deviſed wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes wherin theſe officers are imployed: fourthlie with the falſe maintenance and livings fiftlie are mingled with the knowne profane / ignorant and diſordered perſons which are joint members with them in their aſſemblies.</p>
            <p>This is the ſomme of my faith / and allegeance to my God and my Prince / here is the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of the wholle difference which is betweene me and the clergy of this land / and the ſomme of the whole cauſe for the which I and divers other of my poore brethren are judged to be ſchiſmatikes / felons / heretikes: If this may come to the Royall hands of my ſouueraygne and to the veiwe of theyr H. H. they will be ſoone induced that neyther I nor any other that hold the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:548:3"/>with me deſerve the ſhortning of our dayes by her Maieſties ſword for theſe things</p>
            <p>And here is all that euer wee hold. As towching that error / concerning the repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Lords praye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r / wherewith wee are charged / far be it even far be it that wee ſhould deny the ſame or anie the like ſcripture / to be an holy forine of prayer which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth not only an e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quiſite paterne of doctrine which a Chriſtian ſoule may not onlie lawfully ſay / but alſo with great comfort have the vſe of the ſame: In deed wee rather hold it for a doctrine then prayer / the abuſe in the often repeating of it / wee condemne and this I am ſure was the judgement in this point of thoſe holy ſervants of God who nowe reſt from their labors. The good which this land getreth outwardite by theſe falſe offices afornamed and the livings belonging vnto them is / the traytors (as Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtes and Seminary Prieſts are drawen by that hope they have of poſſeſſing this Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh gould / to become the vnnaturall betrayers of theyr naturall Prince and Contrye into the hands of ſtrangers: wheras if theſe offices and livings were by publique au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority once removed and converted to her Maieſtyes vſe / the Pope would have no oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſion to ſend over theſe locaſtes / they would be no baytes to alluer them hether and the home Papiſtes would be vtterly voyde of hope to ſee their expected day / ſo that the main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayning of theſe offices and livings / theyr deviſed workes and callings would fall: with them is ioyned that there is no ſmall danger of her Maieſticall perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the whole ſtate of this land / I doe point but at the inconueniences which in conſcience towards her Maieſtye and my contrie / I am bond to ſhew / they that are wiſer will thinke of the cauſe with ſeriouſnes / and would not I hope thinke me worthie to be ſmitten for this ſhewing the danger.</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer I hold in theſe points controverted I hold the ſame of meere conſcience towards God / of that meere deſtetation which in conſcience I am boud to have of all the inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions of men or Angels in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and of that care which I ought to have of the ſalvation and ſafegarde of her Maieſtie whome the Lord preſerve for ever more and of my contrie. I have for my warrant not onlie the written word which is ſufficient / but alſo in the points of greateſt moment / the doctrine of the Church of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d eſtabliſhed by her Maieſtie and theyr Honors togeather with the writtings / teſtimonies and blood of the famous ſervants and Martyrs of Chriſt viz. M. whickleff. M. Brute. M. Aſhly. M. Parvy. M. Charch and many other holy witneſſes of the Lord in former tymes M. Tindall M. Lambert. M. Latymer. M. Bale the famous ſervantes of God in this later age togeather with the witneſſes of the reformed Churches at this day / in the points I ſay of ſpeciall waight / my ſoule is ſo evinced by the word of God in all them as I am ready to give my lyfe by the ayde of my God for the truth of this teſtimony and the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of the fornamed ſervants of God and holy Churches of Chriſt: yet if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can ſee by the written word of God that I erre in any thing / I will moſt willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme my iudgement / crave pardon erneſthe for any overſight: yea and be moſt willing to ſuffer due puniſhement for my temeritie: But if on the other ſide I teſtify nothing but verity in theſe points I am vndoubtedlie perſuaded of: I moſt humblie crave that the percing edge of that ſword may not in heat be turned againſt me and my brethren which was never profeſſedlie violent againſt the open and ſworne enemies of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Prince and contrie.</p>
            <p>Death / I thanke God I feare not in this cauſe eſpeciallie / for I know that the ſting of death is taken away and that they are bleſſed which die in the Lord for witneſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the former corruptions <hi>Reu. 14.9.13.</hi> Life I deſyre not if I be guiltie of ſedition / of defaming and diſturbing the quiet ſtate of her Maieſtie peceable governement.</p>
            <p>Laſtlie / I moſt humblie and earneſtlie beſeech theyr Honors and worſhips in whoſe handes this writting of myne ſhall come to conſider that it is to no purpoſe that her
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:548:3"/>
               <hi>Maieſtyes ſubjects ſhovld beſtow their tyme in learning in ſtudie and meditation of th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> word, in reading the writtings and doings of learned men and of the holy martirs whic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have ben in former ages, eſpecially the writings publiſhed by her Majeſties auctoritie, they may not without danger proffeſſe and hold thoſe truths as which they learne out of th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and that in ſuch ſorte as they are able to conuince all the world that will ſtand againſt th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by noe other weapons then by the word of God. I beſeech them alſo to conſider what a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable cauſe it is that wee may hold fellowſhip with the Romiſh Church in the inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions thereof without al danger &amp; canot without extreme peril be permited in Iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; practiſe to diſſent from the ſame where it ſwerueth from the true waye, &amp; as they find the things to be of eſpeciall moment in religion, I beſeech them in the bowels of Ieſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt to be a meanes vnto her Majeſtie &amp; their H. Hs. that my cauſe may be waighed in even balance, impriſonments, Indightments arainme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts yea death it ſelfe are no meete wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pons to conuince the conſcience grounded vpon the word of God &amp; accompanyed with ſo manie wittneſſes of his famous ſeruants &amp; Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>The Lord bleſſe hir right excellent Majeſtie my moſt gracious ſoveraigne bleſſe their H. Hs this whole land &amp; all his ſaincts even for his great names ſake. Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Subſcribed with heart &amp; hand by me Iohn penry now in ſtraight bonds for the former teſtimonie of Chriſts truth.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>TO THE DISTRESSED FAITHFVLL CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GREGATION OF CHRIST IN LONDON, AND ALL THE Members thereof, wither in bondes or at liberty theſe be delivered.<lb/>
My beloved brethren M. F. Iohnſon M. D. M, S M. S. M. G. I. M. I M. H. M. B. M. S. R. B. M, R. M K N. B. M. B. I. M, N P. W. C. P A. my brethren M. I. C. W. B. A. P. M. MM. E, C. C D. G. M. A B. With the reſt of you both men &amp; women (as if particularly I named you all) which ſtand members of this poore afflicted congregation whether at libertie or in bondes, Ieſus Chriſt that great king &amp; Prince of the kings of the earth bleſſe you comfort you with his invincible ſpirit, that you may be able to beare and over come theſe great trials which you are yet (and I with you if I live to vndergoe for his names ſake in this teſtimonie.</salute>
            </opener>
            <opener>
               <salute>BELOVED</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>let vs thinke out lot and portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more then bleſſed that novve are vouch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaffed the favor not onelie to know &amp; to profeſſe, but alſo to ſuffer for the ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Goſpell: &amp; let vs remember, that great is our reward in heaven; if wee endure vnto the end. I teſtifie vnto you for mine one part as I ſhal anſwere before Ieſus Chriſt &amp; his elect Angels that I never ſaw anie truth more cleare &amp; vndoubted then this witneſſe wherin wee ſtand, 1 againſt falſe offices. 2 the callings. 3 the workes. 4. the maintenance left &amp; retayned in this land by and from Poperie: 5. againſt the obedience wich ſpiritually eyther in ſoule or in body is yealded, &amp; the comunion that is had with theſe inventions of darknes. 6, the mingling of all ſorts in theſe aſſemblies. 7. the worſhip do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne but ſcant in one of the three partes of the commiſſion given by our ſauiour Scant done I ſay in one of the three partes of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion, by the beſt teachers of this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, And I thanke my God I am not only ready to be bound &amp; baniſhed but eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to die in this cauſe by his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth yea my brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I greatly lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in regard of my ſelf to be diſolued, and to liue in the bleſſed king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of heaven with Ieſus <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:548:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:548:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:548:5"/>Chriſt and his Angels, with Adam Henoch, Noah, Abraham, Moſes, Iobe. Dauid, Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, Daniel, Paule the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles, and with the reſt of the holy, ſaints both men and women, with the glorious kinges, Prophets and martyrs, and wittneſſes of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt that have bine from the begining of the world, particulerly with my twoe deare brethren maſter Henry Barrowe &amp; maſter Iohn Greenwoode which have laſt of all yealded their bloud for this precious teſtimonie: Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſing vnto you my btethren and ſiſters that if I might liue vppon this earth the days of Methuſhelach twyſe tould and that in noe leſſe comforte then Peter Iames, and Iohn were in the mount, and after this life might be ſure of the knigdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that yet to gayne al this I durſt not goe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the former teſtimony. Wher fore my brethren I beſeech you be of like minde herein with me, I doubt, not but you have the ſame precious faith with me &amp; are pertakers alſo of farte more glorious comfort, then my barren. and ſinfull ſoule cane be, ſtriue for me &amp; with me, that the Lord our God, may make me and vs all able to ende our courſe with ioy and patience: Striue alſo that he may ſtaye his bleſsed hand [if it be his good pleaſure] and not make any farther breach in his Church by the taking awaye of any more of vs as yet to the diſcouraging of the weake and the lifting vp of the horne of our aduerſaries. I would indeed if it be his good pleaſure liue yet with you, to helpe you to beare that greueous and hard yoake which yet ye are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to ſuſtaine eyther here or in a ſtrange land. And my good brethren ſeing baniſhement with loſſe of goodes is likely to betyde you all. preparcy our ſelues for this hard entreatie and reioyce that you are made worthy for CHRIST cauſe to ſuffer and beare al theſe things: And I beſeech you in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt, that none of you in this caſe loke vppon his perticular eſtate but regard the generall ſtate of the Church of God that the ſame may goe and be kept together whetherſoeuer it ſhal pleaſe God to ſend you. Oh the bleſſinge wilbe great that ſhall enſue this care, whereas if you goe euery man to prouid for his owne houſe, and to loke for his owne familie. Firſt neglecting pore Sion, the Lord will ſett his face againſt you and ſcatter you from the one end of heaven to the other, neyther ſhall you finde a reſting place for the ſoles of your feet or a bleſing vppon any thing you take in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
            <p>The Lord my brethren and ſiſters. hath not forgotten to be gracious vnto Sion you ſhall yet finde dayes of peace and of reſt if you continew faith full: This Stampeing &amp; treading of vs vnder his feete this ſubuerting of our cauſe, and right in iudgement is done by him to the end that we ſhoul ſearch and trie our wayes, and repent vs of our careleſsnes profannes and rebellion in his ſight, but he wil yet maintaine the cauſe of our ſoules and redeeme our liues, if we returne to him yea he wilbe with vs in fire &amp; water &amp; wil not forſakevs if our harts be only and eſpecially of the building of Sion whetherſoeuer we goe. Let not thoſe of you then that either haue ſtocks in your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, or ſome likly trades to liue by diſpoſe of your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues where it may be moſt commodious for your outward eſtate and in the meane tyme ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the poore ones that have no ſuch meanes, eyther to beare the whole worke vpon their weake ſhoulders, or to ende their daies in ſorowe and morning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for want of outward and inward co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts in the land of ſtrangers for the Lord wil be an auenger of all ſuch dealings. But couſult with the whole Church, yea with the brethten of other places, how the church may be kept togeather and built whetherſoeuer they go, let not the poore and the freendleſſe be forced to ſtay behinde heere and to breake a good conſcience for want of your ſupport and kindneſſe vnto them that they may go with you, and here I humbly beſeech you, not in anie outward regard, as I ſhall anſwer before my God. that you would take my pore and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late widowe and my meſſe of fatherleſſe and freindleſſe orphaines with you into exile whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoeuer you goe, and you ſhall fynde I doubt not that the bleſſed promeſſes of my God made vnto me and myne will accompanie them, &amp; even the whole Church for their fakes for this alſo is the Lords promiſe vnto the holy ſeede) as you ſhall not need much to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, what they ſhal eate, or wherwith they ſhal be clothed, and in ſhorte time I doubt not but they wilbe found helpfull &amp; not burthenſome to the Church only I beſeech you <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:548:5"/>I and, where they muſt be enforced, to goe againe vnto Egypte. and my God wil bleſſe you euen with a ioyfull retourne vnto your owne country for it. there are of you, whoe I doubt not wilbe carefull of the performance of the will of your deade brother in this poynt, whoe may yet liue to ſhew this kindeneſſe vnto youres, I wil ſay noe more. Be kinde louinge and tender harted, the one of you towardes the other, laboure every way to encreaſe love and to ſhew the duties of love one of you towardes an other, by viſitinge, comfortinge and relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one the other euen for the reproach of the heathen that are round about vs (as the Lord ſaith.) Be watching in prayer eſpecially remember thoſe of out brethren that are eſpeciallye endaungered, perticulerly thoſe our twoe brethren M. Studley and Robert Boule whome our God hath ſtrengthned now to ſtand in the forefront of the battell. I feare me that our ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>releſnes was over great to ſue vnto our God for the liues of theſe towe ſo notable lights of his Church who nowe reſt with him, and that he tooke them away for many reſpects ſeeming good to his wiſdome, ſoe alſo that we might learne to be more carefull in prayer in all ſuch cauſes, pray for them then my brethren and for our brother M. Fran: Iohnſ: and for me, who am likely to end my dayes eyther with them or before them that our God may ſpare vs vnto his church if it be his God pleaſure, or giue vs exceding faythfullnes and be euery way comfortable vnto the ſiſter and wife of the dead</p>
            <p>I meane vnto my beloued M. Barrowe and M. Greenwoode whome I moſt hartly ſalute, and deſire much to be comforted in theyr God whoe by his blesſinges from aboue, wil counteruayle vnto them, the want of ſoe notable a broher and huſband. I would wiſh you earneſtly to write, yea to ſend if you may to comforte the brethren in the weſt, and North countreys, that they faint not in theſe troubles, and, that alſoe you may have of theyr aduiſe and they of youres what to doe in theſe deſolate times. and if you thinke it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing for theyr further comfort and direction ſend them conuenientlie a copy of this my letter, and of the declaration of my faith, and alegiance wiſhinge them before whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they be called that theyr owne mouthes, be not had a witneſſe againſt them in any thnge: yea I would wiſh you and them to be together if you may whetherſoeuer you ſhalbe baniſhed and to this purpoſe to bethinke you before hand where to be, yea to ſend ſome whoe may be meet to prepare you ſome reſting place, &amp; be al of you aſſured that he whoe is your god in England, wilbe your God in any land vnder the whole heaven for the earth, and the fulnes thereof are his, and bleſſed are they that for his cauſe are bereaued of a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny parte of the ſame! Finally my brethren the eternall God bleſſe you, and youres, that I may meete with you all vnto my comfort in the bleſſed kingdome of heauen, Thus haujng from my harte and, with teares performed (it may be) my laſt duetje towardes you in this life I ſalute you all in the Lorde both men and wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, even thoſe whoe I have not named, as hartelie as thoſe whoſe names I haue mentioned, [for all your names I knowe not] And remember to ſtand ſteedfaſt, and faithfull in Ieſus Chriſt, as you haue receiued him vnto your immortality: And he conferme and eſtabliſh you to the ende for the praiſe of his glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>The 24 the of the 4 moneth Aprill. 1593.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your louinge brother in the patience and ſufferinges of the goſpell Iohn Penry, a wittneſſe of Chriſt in this life and a pertaker of the glory that ſhalbe reuealed.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
